Finding Aid for the Everett Long Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Everett Long Papers
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0265
25.84 linear feet
Everett Long Papers
Preliminary inventory of contents (very general and approximate)
July 2011
Pete Finney
pcfinney@inbox.com
- Misc. clippings, mostly from ‘80s and ‘90s fairly thoroughly filed by subject (in file folders), with many coming from “alternative weeklies”, and some from daily papers and mainstream magazines. Little (if any) of it relates directly to Long himself. (Box 1)
- Some topics: (Box 2)
  Politics and news (many sub-topics with separate folders), music, humor, Nashville, and a collection of the weekly syndicated “News of the Weird.“
- There are a lot of clippings in some of these folders, some quite small. If he only wanted one paragraph he often just cut out the one paragraph, so many of the folders are overflowing with small bits of paper. (Box 3)
- My subjective take on these first four boxes: There’s an incredible amount of raw material for anyone interested in political or cultural subjects from the 80s-90s, with a slant towards the left-wing, countercultural, and just plain quirky. (Box 4)
- Contains a folder with 3 ½ issues (out of 5 total?) of the 1970 Nashville Breakdown “underground” paper which Long was involved in. (Box 5)
- There is another (large) folder of copies of Common Ground from 1990-91, a progressive and community oriented paper (monthly?) with both a national staff and a local one; the content is a mixture of local and national stories. (Box 5)
- The remainder of the box (about 80%) is a collection of comic strips cut out and filed in folders by name; some of these are fairly mainstream strips from daily papers, some are from “alternative” papers. There are maybe 25 different comics in all? (Box 5)
- This box consists of various political papers and clippings, mostly from the 1970s, filed by subject. (Box 6)
- There is a folder on the Southern Student Organizing Committee with personal letters and documents. This also includes a transcription of Long’s interview with Gregg Michel, for Michel’s doctoral dissertation on the SSOC, which was published as “Struggle for a Better South” in 2004. (Box 6)
- This box contains press clippings on the “Nashville Movement” filed by year, from 2001-2006. (Box 7)
- It also contains folders of various community newsletters and papers from the era, in full. (Box 7)
- This box contains full manuscripts (copied) of various books (and dissertations), none written by Long as far as I could tell. (Box 9)
- There is also one large box (200 pages?) of meticulously copied press clippings. I did not get into it enough to be able to describe the contents, but did wonder if this might be Long’s own compiling of some of his material from the rest of the collection. It seems to me this would be well worth further investigation. (Box 9)